<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Enrichment analysis workshop material on Functional Analysis</title>
    <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Enrichment analysis workshop material on Functional Analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/intro/</guid>
      <description>Link to intro slides?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enrichment analysis statistics</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/stats/</guid>
      <description>Check out the toy enrichment calculater here
 QUESTION: If 17 of the 168 differentially expressed genes are annotated with the 500-gene term of interest. Is it significant?
 Smaller backround (e.g. proteomic dataset) Fewer annotation terms tested?  QUESTION : How many of the of the 168 differentially expressed genes have to be annotated with a 500-gene term of interest for it to be significant at p=0.05?
 What about a term with 30 annotated genes?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example: SH-SY5Y Differentiation</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/example-dataset/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/example-dataset/</guid>
      <description>SH-SY5Y Differentiation SH-SY5Y is a commonly used neuroblastoma cell line. With appropriate treatment, it can be induced to differentiate into a ‘more neuronal’ form. Differentiated cells look quite different, growing thin neurites out from the body of the cell.
Image from Figure 4 (Pezzini et al. 2017)
The question: What pathways are involved in SH-SY5Y Differentiation? In their paper Transcriptomic Profiling Discloses Molecular and Cellular Events Related to Neuronal Differentiation in SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma Cells Pezzini et al induced differentiation of the SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma cell line and measured transcriptomic changes via RNAseq (Pezzini et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the genelist</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/genelists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/genelists/</guid>
      <description>SH-SY5Y is a widely-used neuroblastoma cell line. With approriate treatment, they can be readily differentiated from their base state into a more neuronal phenotype.
In their paper Transcriptomic Profiling Discloses Molecular and Cellular Events Related to Neuronal Differentiation in SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma Cells Pezzini et al induced differentiation of the SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma cell line and measured transcriptomic changes via RNAseq (Pezzini et al. 2017).
Here are some differential expression results from their raw data: http://degust.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enrichment Tools</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/enrichment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/enrichment/</guid>
      <description>Enrichment in gProfiler? Try gprofiler GOSt for functional enrichment: https://biit.cs.ut.ee/gprofiler/gost
Using the 168 differentially expressed gene list.
NB: Set the background gene list with _Advanced Options &amp;gt; Statistical Domain scope &amp;gt; Custom : Paste in genelist _
Enrichment in DAVID (Maybe skip?) Main point is that different tools give different results despite using the same databases! Though david has some nice features.
Try calculating funtional enrichment in DAVID: https://david.ncifcrf.gov/</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/resources/</guid>
      <description>List of useful tools with description.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End of Session Challenge</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/challenge/</guid>
      <description>Dr Dodge&amp;rsquo;s Experiment There&amp;rsquo;s quite a few ways you can calculate functional enrichment - so there&amp;rsquo;s always a risk of p-hacking, wheather accidental or deliberate.
So lets go deliberate&amp;hellip;
Dr Dodge is convinced that your experiment should turn out with relevance to GO term &amp;lsquo;segmentation&amp;rsquo; - but p=0.06! But they must be significant, the paper has to be submitted by Friday!
What hacky and statsticically questionable approaches could you apply to call these results &amp;ldquo;significant&amp;rdquo;?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>