<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Modules on Functional Analysis</title>
    <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Modules on Functional Analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Basics</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/basics/</guid>
      <description>Functional analysis of -Omics data Overview of enrichment methods  Types  Gene list based Rank Based Network based  Hypogeometric distribution and Fisher&amp;rsquo;s exact test  Over/under representation? Background list Select organism Difference between database and tool and both  What is GO? A tree. Other stats considerations:
 Multiple hypothesis correction Importance of background, what is it. Effect of gene list size? What size do you need?  The -log pval plot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/overview/</guid>
      <description>Functional analysis of -Omics data General information The workshop covers the bioinformatics concepts and tools available for interpreting a gene list using gene ontology and pathway information. The workshop focuses on the principles and concepts required for analyzing and conducting functiona and pathway analysis on a gene list from any organism, although focus will be on human and model eukaryotic organisms.
Course Objectives Participants will gain practical experience and skills to be able to:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Data Preparation</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/example-data-preparation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 12:17:28 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/module/example-data-preparation/</guid>
      <description>SH-SY5Y is a widely-used neuroblastoma cell line. With approriate treatment, they can be readily differentiated from their base state into a more neuronal phenotype.
In their paper Transcriptomic Profiling Discloses Molecular and Cellular Events Related to Neuronal Differentiation in SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma Cells Pezzini et al induced differentiation of the SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma cell line and measured transcriptomic changes via RNAseq (Pezzini et al. 2017).
This document describes a simple reanalysis of their raw data, to produce the results browseable through degust here</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>