<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Notes on Functional Analysis</title>
    <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/notes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Notes on Functional Analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 16:30:37 +1000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/notes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Basics</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/notes/basics/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/notes/basics/</guid>
      <description>Functional analysis of -Omics data Notes, to be removed
Overview of enrichment methods  Types  Gene list based Rank Based Network based  Hypogeometric distribution and Fisher&amp;rsquo;s exact test  Over/under representation? Background list Select organism Difference between database and tool and both  What is GO? A tree. Other stats considerations:
 Multiple hypothesis correction Importance of background, what is it. Effect of gene list size? What size do you need?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Activities</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/notes/activities/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 16:30:37 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/notes/activities/</guid>
      <description>This is to be merged into sections by topic.
Activity - Getting a list of DE genes SH-SY5Y is a widely-used neuroblastoma cell line. With approriate treatment, they can be readily differentiated from their base state into a more neuronal phenotype.
In their paper Transcriptomic Profiling Discloses Molecular and Cellular Events Related to Neuronal Differentiation in SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma Cells Pezzini et al induced differentiation of the SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma cell line and measured transcriptomic changes via RNAseq (Pezzini et al.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>