<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Functional Analysis of -Omics Data on Functional Analysis</title>
    <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Functional Analysis of -Omics Data on Functional Analysis</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/intro/</guid>
      <description>Link to intro slides?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enrichment Statistics</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/stats/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/stats/</guid>
      <description>Enrichment statistics are based on a contingency table like so:
   Gene ..in term ..not in term Total     ..in gene list 50 100 150   ..not in gene list (but in background) 200 15900 16100   Total 250 16000 16250    This is based on the 16250 genes that were measured in your experiment.
Note that there might be extra genes that weren&amp;rsquo;t measured these are excluded from the calculations entirely.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Analysis</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/example-dataset/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/example-dataset/</guid>
      <description>SH-SY5Y Differentiation SH-SY5Y is a commonly used neuroblastoma cell line. With appropriate treatment, it can be induced to differentiate into a ‘more neuronal’ form. Differentiated cells look quite different, growing thin neurites out from the body of the cell.
Image is derived from Figure 4 (Pezzini et al. 2017)
The question: What pathways are involved in SH-SY5Y Differentiation? In their paper Transcriptomic Profiling Discloses Molecular and Cellular Events Related to Neuronal Differentiation in SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma Cells Pezzini et al induced differentiation of the SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma cell line and measured transcriptomic changes via RNAseq (Pezzini et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defining the genelist</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/genelists/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/genelists/</guid>
      <description>Starting from those differential expression results here, how do we go about getting a genelist to calculate enrichment on?
Activities  Download the full table of data from degust. Import into excel. Import --
 How many genes are differentially expressed? In these results the FDR Column contains the corrected p-value, and the &amp;lsquo;differentiated&amp;rsquo; column shows the log2 fold-change of differentiated cells vs untreated cells (log2(diff)-log2(undiff)). 0 is unchanged.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enrichment Tools</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/enrichment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/enrichment/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;re going to use the small 168-gene set for all these enrichment tools. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have them already, they are available here:
As gene symbols (CD2, DLG4 e.t.c).
 168-gene differentially expressed gene list Background list  As ensemble gene ids (e.g. ENSG00000183654). Harder to read, but some tools need unambiguous IDs like this for performance reasons when working with larger geneslists; e.g. PANTHER or DAVID background or STRING without a specified organism.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resources</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/resources/</guid>
      <description>The following tools might be useful for downstream functional analysis; this includes some not covered in todays workshop.
Note that most of these tools do more than just enrichment tests, and some include their own databases.
g:Profiler / g:GOSt https://biit.cs.ut.ee/gprofiler/gost
The g:GOSt &amp;lsquo;functional profiling&amp;rsquo; tool of g:Profiler calculates It has a clean modern interface and a handy summary of which genes contribute to the enrichment.
PANTHER http://www.pantherdb.org/
PANTHER performs overrepresentation tests across multiple databases; Gene ontology, reactome, PANTHER pathways and protein classes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>End of Session Challenge</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/challenge/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/content/challenge/</guid>
      <description>Dr Dodge&amp;rsquo;s Experiment There&amp;rsquo;s quite a few ways you can calculate functional enrichment - so there&amp;rsquo;s always a risk of p-hacking, whether accidental or deliberate.
So lets go deliberate&amp;hellip;
Dr Dodge is convinced that your experiment should turn out with relevance to GO term &amp;lsquo;segmentation&amp;rsquo; - but p=0.06! But they must be significant, the paper needs be submitted by Friday!
What hacky and statistically questionable approaches could you apply to call these results &amp;ldquo;significant&amp;rdquo;?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Data Preparation</title>
      <link>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/supplementary/example-data-preparation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2019 12:17:28 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://monashbioinformaticsplatform.github.io/enrichment_analysis_workshop/supplementary/example-data-preparation/</guid>
      <description>SH-SY5Y is a widely-used neuroblastoma cell line. With approriate treatment, they can be readily differentiated from their base state into a more neuronal phenotype.
In their paper Transcriptomic Profiling Discloses Molecular and Cellular Events Related to Neuronal Differentiation in SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma Cells Pezzini et al induced differentiation of the SH-SY5Y Neuroblastoma cell line and measured transcriptomic changes via RNAseq (Pezzini et al. 2017).
This document describes a simple reanalysis of their raw data, to produce the results browseable through degust here</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>